BASSAM ALHARBI

Experienced software engineer with a passion for developing innovative software that accelerates the efficiency and effectiveness of organizational success. Well versed in technology and writing code to create reliable and easy-to-use systems. Interested in all modern technologies that help develop modern programs. Currently, I am developing web platforms and using the necessary web technologies.

Contact Information

bsalharbi00@gmail.com | Github | Linkedin

Work Experience

Software Engineer

Elm

May 2023 – Present Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

Elm Company is a Saudi Joint Stock Company owned by Saudi Public Investment Fund (PIF), it is specialized in providing secure electronic services, and has been in existence since 1988 as a technical research and development lab for the Saudi Ministry of Interior.

Absher

Absher platform is the electronic platform of the Ministry of Interior. It aims to provide the services of the Saudi Ministry of Interior digitally and in an integrated manner to citizens, residents and visitors, by taking advantage of technical capabilities and harnessing modern technologies. This provides an excellent user experience through automated services with high reliability, security and efficiency.

- Develope and maintain Absher services
- Squad lead and responsible to achieve several absher services.
- Contributed to training and mentoring new joiners to the team.

Technologies used

Java (*up to jdk8*), Spring framework, Spring Boot, IBM WebSphere Application Server, IBM WebSphere Portal, IBM WebSphere MQ, Redis, Jenkins, IBM DataPower, IBM Db2 Jira, Bitbucket

Software Engineer / Full Stack Developer

TAHAKOM

June 2022 - May 2023 Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

Full-time job

Saudi Technology and Security Comprehensive Control Company (Tahakom) is one of Tahakom Investment affiliated companies, established on 17/11/1436 H - 01/09/2015, based in Riyadh and operates in all regions of the

Kingdom. The company vision is to be a leader in leveraging innovative technologies to safeguard and enrich people's journeys and enhance public safety.

• Team lead in several project

Designing and implementing platforms for all the departments while practicing agile methodology to achieve high velocity in delivery in multiple projects.

Intifaa

Intifaa is platform for Human Resource department to present offers or special offers to the company's employees so that they can benefit from them through the platform

Some achievements include

- Team lead for this project in the Backend and Frontend
- Participated in the Intifaa Revamp docs project.
- Participated in establishing the software practices used by the Intifaa (Pull Requests, Code Review, Unit Tests, etc...) to assure high quality of the software.
- Participated in the Architecture and Design of the Intifaa Platform.

Notification Center

Notification center is platform to integrate with multiple SMS providers to send and schedule the messages.

- Combine the projects repository as Monorepo concept to one single repository.
- Create the CI scripts for building projects

Technologies used

Java (*up to jdk17*), Spring framework, Spring Boot, Spring Cloud, Hibernate, Typescript, Angular, Docker, Openshift, SQL Server, Gitlab, Gitlab CI/CD

Software Engineer / Freelancer

Semi

Jan 2022 – 06/2022

Part-time job as freelancer

Semi is a startup company that aimed to design and build a e-commerce website for clients.

- I have built the backend of Semi webiste with Spring framework.
- Develop and Maintain websites linked with Salla for clients.

Education

B.S. Software Engineering

Hafr Al Batin University, Hafr Al Batin Saudi Arabia Sep 2017 - June 2022

Certifications

Simplilearn - Full Stack Java Developer

Jun 2021

License: Simplilearn

Udemy - Java Programming Masterclass

Sep 2019

License: Udemy

Udemy - Spring & Hibernate June 2020

License: Udemy

Skills

- Good understanding of OOP & Functional style programming.
- Good understanding Test Driven Development and Unit, Integration, E2E Testing.
- Agile Methodologies Scrum, Kanban.
- Good knowledge in Linux Configuration & shell scripting.
- Basic understanding of the some compilers architecture, e.g. GCC, GraalVM and others.
- Distributed Programming, messaging, stream processing and data pipelines (RabbitMQ, Kafka, JMS).
- Good background in Web Services (SOAP-based and REST).
- Experience with full-Stack Web Development (Angular, Vue.js, Mustache.js, and others).
- Basic knowledge Linux programming (syscalls, filesystems, namespaces and others).
- Basic knowledge of IBM solutions (IBM WebSphere Portal, IBM WebShpere Application Service, IBM WebShepere MQ, IBM Db2, IBM DataPower)
- Good understanding of RDBMS, NoSQL databases, Big Data and Database Sharding techniques.
- Basic knowledge and experience about NoSQL solutions such as MongoDB, Redis.
- Experience in different RDBMS Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL, IBM db2.
- Basic understanding of Unicode and other related char encoding standards.
- Basic understanding of OSI model and related protocols (TCP, UDP, DNS, ARP, FTP, SSH, TLS), and basic knowledge about networking tools like iptables, wireshark, tcpdump, and more.
- Understanding of OIDC and OAuth 2.0 protocols.
- Hands-on experience in Jenkins, Bitbucket pipelines, Docker, Docker Compose, Kubernetes, k3s and AWS.
- Basic knowledge about Data analysis using Python Pandas.

Languages

- · Arabic Native
- English Professional working proficiency